[music]
Right? So, I keep saying long-term. I
said this multiple times in the earlier
lectures, also. Uh but what really is
long-term? Right? So,
we'll try to quantify that now.
Right? By introducing the notion of
something called return.
[clears throat]
Right?
Um
[snorts]
So, this is a common notation that I'll
use throughout where capital T indicates
the timestamp of the end of the episode.
Right? T means the end of the episode.
Right? Essentially, I've reached S plus.
Right? So, this could This is the most
natural way of thinking about long-term
return.
Correct?
It's the most natural way of thinking
about long-term return.
And uh if there if that capital T is
actually finite,
right? So, this is actually this is not
a bad idea. And I'll sum up all the
reward I'm going to get in the future,
and I'll try to optimize that. Okay?
Uh so, again, you can see that
if I try to optimize each one of these
individually, what will happen?
[clears throat]
I might get a very high RT plus one and
RT plus two, but it might put me in such
a bad S T plus two. From then on, even
if I behave optimally,
individually for each of these, these
numbers might be small.
Right? So, what I really want to do is
behave in such a way that even if some
of these numbers are small,
right? Overall, in the future, the sum
that I'm going to get should be
the maximum.
Right? So, overall sum should be
maximum. So, that's essentially the
goal that I have here.
All right.
[snorts]
So, this is fine. It works fine. There's
one circumstance where this won't work.
When T is I mean, there is no end,
right? So, you just keep doing this for
forever.
If I If I If I keep solving a problem
forever, then it becomes a problem. And
not necessarily forever. If I'm also
doing something over a very very very
long horizon. If T is very large, not
necessarily infinite, but T is very
large also, I get into
some issues.
Okay, because this will become a
quantity with a large variance.
Right? So, one other thing I should
point out, this is something which
people miss and get confused uh
sometimes while reading uh on their own.
So, T here
is a
random variable.
Right?
So, every time
I run the system,
it might stop at a different time.
Like, think of playing chess, right?
There is a finite end point. Chess will
end.
But every time I play the game, I don't
stop at the same number of moves.
Right? Even something like tic-tac-toe,
right? Even though there's an upper
limit on the number of moves you can
make,
right? It's not necessary that you'll
always end up playing
five moves.
Like, you might end You might win in
four moves. You might win in Well, yeah,
if you win in three moves,
uh well, okay.
Uh your opponent is really bad. But uh
so, you could win in three moves. You
could win in four moves, or you could
win in five moves, right? Or or you
could not win at all. I mean, so you
could still end up drawing the game.
Uh so, like that, so T is a random
variable. So, when I put T here, it
doesn't mean it always runs for
some T steps, okay? So, every time I run
it, it'll be a different value for T.
So, remember that. Right? And
consequently, GT is also a random
variable because all of these are random
variables. I'm talking about sums of
random variables.
Okay? And a random number of those
random variables are being summed up.
Okay? So, GT is also a
random variable that denotes the return.
Okay, great. So, another notion of
return that people typically use is
[cough]
Right?
In fact, I can even do
that.
Okay? So, go back and think about it
purely from a mathematical perspective.
So, if my sum is going to run till
infinity,
and my gamma is less than one,
and remember that individually each R is
bounded,
okay? So, this sum will converge to
something finite. So, I don't have to
worry about what I had in this case.
This sum will not explode. Okay, so that
is fine.
Right? But, there's even something more
interesting about this uh discounted
reward formulation. In fact, uh
originally, when people proposed a
discounted reward formulation, it was
not really from the boundedness point of
view. It was more from a
Huh?
From a psychology point of view.
Huh? Immediate gratification versus
delayed gratification.
[snorts]
Right? So, if you're Let's look at what
happens if gamma is zero.
[clears throat]
Everything will go, right? It's just RT
plus one. This goes back to
just optimizing for the immediate
immediate payoff, right? So, this gives
you
essentially you are going to behave in a
way so that
the next time step, what is the maximum
reward that you're going to get? So,
you're going to behave only in that way.
Right?
So, if we think about what gamma is
doing, so it's making Suppose I get a 10
here
versus getting a 10 here.
So, 10 here is more valuable than 10
here.
Right?
And of course, 10 here is more valuable
than 10 here.
Right?
So, let's go back to our
robot grasping problem.
We're talking about having a minus one
all the time and then giving you a
hundred when you actually grasp.
So, instead of that, I can say I'm going
to use a discounted rewards.
My gamma is say 0.8.
So, what does it mean?
So, the sooner I grasp it,
the larger the value I'm going to see.
Correct? So, the overall reward I'm
starting from here,
I should put myself in a trajectory so
that I grasp this quickly.
Right? Otherwise, I'll see some gamma
power
10,000 into
100.
So, that's a very very small value. So,
the shorter I So, I know I can get rid
of the minus one.
Right? So, I don't really have to do the
minus one. But then, what what becomes
tricky here?
I have to figure out what's the right
value of gamma.
[snorts]
Right? So, that becomes tricky.
So, so this is
[clears throat and snorts]
Okay.
So, they used this kind of gamma to
control for whether you are a
near-sighted agent who only worried
about immediate gratification or whether
you are okay delaying the gratification
a little bit so that you get a higher
payoff further down the line.
Why is gamma discounted reward in total
reward case?
There only one one payoff, right?
So,
just pull.
What we don't do cumulative or so.
You're talking about regrets. You're
talking about regrets, right?
You're talking We're talking about the
total reward case, right? So,
uh
Yeah,
having a discount there really doesn't
make sense, right?
So, anyway you're trying to optimize
regret.
Right? So, in in in in some case your
gamma is as small as possible.
And when you say you're optimizing
regret, that means you are trying to
keep your gamma as small as possible.
So, essentially you want all your
winnings to come in one pull.
Right? And one pull, I want to be
optimal.
So, that is your optimal regret case,
right? So, when you're trying to do
achieve something like this, setting a
gamma doesn't make sense.
Right?
But I mean if you can come up with a
different objective function, maybe
there is something that you can think of
over the entire learning process.
Okay.
So, one thing which I should
point out, just let me finish. One thing
I should point out is that
uh classically the RL people, right,
look at bandit problems as immediate RL,
right? I mean the the the learning the
the whole interaction is just that one
arm pull. Okay, that is how we think of
it. While the the long-term case is the
full RL problem. But if you look at the
people who work in the bandit theory
community, right, they think of the
interaction as the entire learning
process.
Right, they don't think of it as one arm
pull. They think of it as the whole
process itself is the the learning
process. So for them it is like an
episode.
Right? So there's a very different
mindset. So the RL people don't think of
it that way. And the bandit people don't
think of discount factors and other
things because that is something which
the RL guys came up with for looking at
long-term payoffs. So
there's a mismatch of vocabulary there.
So maybe that is something to
find that in in the middle ground, but
I'm I'm not sure.
Return is a function of the time step,
yeah.
So we should
try to maximize earlier returns rather
than
later ones.
In which
how what are the outcomes?
Let's put it this way. So I should
optimize my policy in such a way that
wherever I am starting from there and
going forward, I should get maximum
possible return.
But even if I'm in the last step, I
don't want to goof up in the last step.
Right? If if I'm see one thing you
should remember is that if I know where
I'm going to end, if that capital T is
given to me beforehand
then it becomes a
non-stationary problem.
Because I'll know, okay, I have five
more steps to go. What should I do? I
take one more step. I have only four
more steps to go. What should I do? So
immediately the problem changes.
Right? If I know the capital T, then
it's a non-stationary setting, right?
So, we will not we will not look at
cases where the capital T is known.
Okay, we will only look at cases where
capital T is known to be finite, but
not deterministic, right? It's not known
a priori. So, it's not like I can say
that I'll optimize only at the last step
or anything because I don't know what
the last step is.
Right? I might recognize it when I
actually reach it, but I don't know
beforehand that okay, I'm going to have
only so many
steps to go. I mean, this is the normal
setting that we assume.
But you can immediately see it is not
realistic, you know? I mean, when you're
playing chess, you can always say I'm
going to win in three more moves.
Or well, [clears throat] I'm going to
lose in three more moves, depending on
right? So, how how well the game is
going. So, in some cases, you do have
this kind of a little bit of a a
forecasting ability as to what the
capital T is, but typical the basic
setup that we'll talk about will assume
T is unknown.
Uh
yeah.
Do people understand why gamma equal to
one I mean, closer to one is
far-sighted?
Right? And closer to zero is
near-sighted.
Clear? Yeah.
In the second equation, R and T are a
little biased to the action which is
giving us faster reward.
Which one?
Let's say [snorts] I I have five actions
possible, and I picked an action which
is giving me better reward in the first
step. Mhm.
And there is another probability where I
could pick another action first and then
this action later, which is a higher
reward in the longer run.
But then in this equation, we are
actually giving more reward to that uh
action which is Well, depends on
many things, right? Depends on the value
of gamma, and depends on the magnitude
of the other rewards that you're
getting.
Right? So, let's say gamma is .99999999.
Then the bias is low. When the bias is
low. Depending on how far-sighted you
want to be, you have to pick your gamma.
Right? So, they are
unsatisfactory. You have another
free parameter, really free parameter
that you have no way how to tune.
Uh but yeah, it's there.
Right? So, we'll talk about another
reward formulation shortly.
Uh which get gets rid of the gamma, but
makes it very hard to optimize.
Anyway, so any other questions on this?
Sir,
what about negative rewards?
Doesn't matter, yeah. I just add it up.
Does it decrease the amount of reward we
have considered? Yeah, sure.
If an action if an action is
Yeah. Like we gave some minus 100. Yeah.
But if we multiply with 0.5 like 0.25,
it will be like minus 25. Yeah. So,
you're reducing actually the reward
point at the end. But then that means
I'm fall I'm failing after more time
steps, right?
So, I'm okay.
I mean, whether it's positive or
negative, it doesn't matter as far as
this return definitions are concerned.
You are essentially interested in
maximizing the return.
Therefore, if you're going to take an
action that gives you a minus 100
reward, the farther out in the future
you take it, it is better.
Right? So,
succeed for as long as you can and then
die, you know.
Right? So, so yeah, it doesn't matter.
So, the rewards can be positive,
negative Yeah, so reinforcement learning
is this really that the community is a
little weird, right? So, we talk about
positive rewards and negative rewards.
Right? If you look at the psychology
literature, they talk about rewards and
punishments.
Right? For some reason, the RL
community, and if you look at the
[snorts]
um you know, other places, they call it
payoffs, right? Uh or they call it
costs. Negative rewards are called
costs. But in the RL community, somehow
thinks of negative things also as
rewarding. So,
we have positive rewards and we have
negative rewards.
You know, but in the larger scheme of
things, you know, negative things also
improve your experience, you know. They
enrich your life in some way, so you can
think of
negative rewards also.
Anyway, [snorts] so
good.
So this is fine then we'll move on to
one more definition.
I have to get this right.
[snorts]
So what does that do?
This gives [snorts] me the average.
Right? So the more the reward I
accumulate the larger the average is
going to be. Right? So [snorts] for a
finite number of n this makes sense.
Right? But what if I have an infinite
number of rewards in the future?
[snorts]
I I
mild regularity assumptions and
boundedness of the individual Rs
this will be bounded. Okay? What is not
clear is that it will have actually have
a limit.
Might not. Right? In general it might
not have a limit. So you have to put
those additional constraints on the kind
of problems that you're solving. Not all
problems have this defined. Right? Or I
mean you can make some small variations
to this to make sure that all problems
have this limit defined. Okay? So there
are slight different
the limit can be you can play around
with the limit. For example one case
where limit will not exist exist is this
if the sequence is periodic.
Like if the sequence is periodic, then
the limit won't exist.
Right, because it will just keep
oscillating all the time. Right, so in
this case, we use something called the
People know how to handle
limits of periodic sequences?
Use something called the Cesaro's limit,
which essentially looks at the average
over
periods, and let's the number of periods
run to infinity.
Right, so in the The reason the limit
doesn't exist is because you cut the
sequence in the middle of a period.
Right, so if it's So it's going to be
periodic, so you you only take a period
as a unit,
and take the reward over the period.
Right, and then you keep adding that
over
[clears throat]
subsequent periods and take the average.
Right?
And limit as the number of such periods
you consider goes to infinity is called
the Cesaro's limit. Then, in such cases,
limit might exist.
And of course, there are a bunch of
other conditions you have to put on the
actual structure of the problem itself
for it to ensure that this limit exists.
But, for a very broad class of problems,
you can talk about these
limits as well. So, the nice thing about
this kind of a reward the return
definition is that it doesn't have a
pesky
gamma parameter. Right? So, it makes it
nice from a
uh computational point of view not to
have the gamma parameter, but it makes
it little weaker from a with the one of
the original motivations of RL point of
view because it doesn't have the gamma
parameter.
Okay, so gamma parameter allows you to
have
I don't know, some sense personality for
your agent.
Like, is it a near-sighted agent or a
far-sighted agent and so on and so
forth. Right? Uh so, especially people
in neuroscience when they are looking at
modeling uh
[snorts]
uh
reinforcement learning humans, right?
So, they actually have they they they
can think of estimating what is your
gamma
by running experiments with you.
Right, Because it's kind of uh you know
it's it's a it's a personality issue
thing, right? So, some people will tend
to be In fact In fact, there are
uh studies that try to correlate uh the
levels of serotonin in your head
uh to gamma.
[snorts]
Right? So, more the serotonin, uh the
larger the gamma value you have in your
decision making and so on and so forth.
I mean, it's like it's it's it's really
weird
uh how how we seem to have all these
parameters in our head uh tied up with
uh different kinds of uh uh
neurotransmitters.
Right?
Anyway,
uh so, this is called the average
reward.
This is called average reward return.
So, any again any guesses what this is
called?
Discounted return.
[clears throat]
Right?
Huh?
Sorry, I I can't hear you.
Cumulative or total return on Right? So,
people Yeah, if you're going to call
that cumulative, then you have to call
this cumulative discounted
[snorts]
Okay, so there is a very nice uh
um
problem that uh people use for uh
motivating why discounted return is bad.
Okay?
So, let let me try and do that here.
[clears throat]
Um
Okay.
So I'm implying no no theological
leanings here, okay? This just a fun
example.
So that's it.
Okay, that's heaven.
And that's hell.
So the path to heaven has a minus 100
reward.
And the path to hell has a plus 1,000
Right? But once you reach heaven, you
get a plus one infinitely.
Once you reach hell, you get a minus one
infinitely.
[snorts]
Huh?
I said I'm not getting into theology
here, okay? This just a fun example.
Of course, you can always think about
other things, yeah.
No no reward for?
No, anyway you're finished here, right?
[laughter]
This is a This is a transient state. We
don't care.
But then,
if I set gamma is to gamma is 0.1 or
something,
right? You'll prefer going to hell.
Right? If gamma is like 0.9, in fact,
gamma has to be pretty high for you to
go to heaven.
[snorts]
Right? [clears throat] So it's the same
problem. So now gamma becomes part of
the problem definition.
Right? Depending on what value I set for
gamma, my optimal policy itself will
change.
Right? So this is not a desirable state
of affairs. I mean, if you're thinking
about saying, "Okay, here is a problem,
solve it." And if it turns out that if I
use average reward
scenario, which is better?
Huh? Going to heaven is better always.
Doesn't depend on anything. What does it
depend on?
[clears throat]
I'm going to get an infinite number of
plus ones, right? That will
help any my negative things I get
initially. I'm getting a finite value
for negative here. I'm going to get a
minus infinity there and a plus infinity
here, so that trumps anything that
happens here. So, average reward
will tell me that this is the best thing
to do.
But if I'm going to use discounted
returns,
so I'll go up or down
depending on what my gamma is.
Right?
Now, you can immediately see that
discounted return is a more realistic
return
[laughter]
because not everybody is going to
heaven, right?
Anyway,
[clears throat]
that's the fun part.
[snorts]
[clears throat]
Then come to the really the one of the
crux of
of reinforcement learning here, right?
And the full RL
and a lot of the algorithms that we look
at and the notion of a value function.
But we already looked at a value
function. Right? But the value function
we looked at was very
simplistic. Right? So, what did we do
there? We said, "Okay,
average of all the rewards I obtained so
far, right? That is the value function."
Then we had another value which we
looked at, which is the
expected true expected reward that I
should get
if I take an action. Right? So, we
denoted that by Q star.
And then we denoted by Q the average
that I'm maintaining
for this, right?
Um
[snorts]
But here,
we have something more complex.
What do we have here?
We have a policy pi.
Which determines not just the current
reward, but also the sequence that I'm
going to see henceforth, right? So, when
I'm going to talk about the value
function here, I'll talk about something
called
V
of pi.
Right? So, V pi is the value function
associated with
a policy pi.
Right?
So, when I say V pi of
S
[snorts]
So, this is essentially the
the expectation of
So, what should I be taking the
expectation of?
Reward So, returns.
What do you think it is?
I should be taking the expectation of
the returns, right? Because the return
is what I'm looking to
optimize. This is what I should be
predicting. So, in the bandit case, I
was only looking at the reward, so I was
just making out it out of the
expectation of the reward.
And here, I should make it out as the
expectation of
return.
So, given
anything?
Anything else?
[clears throat]
Gamma.
Pi. Pi. Pi. I need to condition it on
pi, right? Because I already have a pi
here, so So, why Why do I need to
condition it on pi? Because my GT is
going to depend on pi. Regardless of
what formulation I'm using,
the subsequent rewards I'm going to get
depend on the actions I take. Right? So,
I nearly need to know what my
pi is. Right? So, I need to condition it
on pi. So, we'll denote it like this.
Right? When I write when I write the pi
here, that means that's the policy I'm
conditioning on. Okay? The expectation
with respect to the distribution
generated by following pi.
Okay? Of GT
given that at time T I started with
state S.
Okay? Does it make sense?
Everyone on board?
Right? So, I'm starting from state S.
I'm following pi. I'm generating one
trajectory. Right? Like this.
Right? So, I start from S.
Okay? Go to some S prime. Go to
S double prime.
So on. Right? So, every time I take an
action. So, I'll take A
A prime, A double prime, and so on.
And I'll get R
R.
Right? This is one one trajectory.
So, like that I'll start from S.
I'll do another trajectory. Then I'll
start from S, I'll do another
trajectory. I'll start from S, I'll do
another trajectory. Then I'll be getting
all these rewards.
Like they have R R R prime
R double prime. Like that I'll get some
R1 prime
R1 double prime, and so on so forth.
Each trajectory I'll get one such
sequence of rewards.
Right? So, I'll add up all of these, or
I'll take a discounted sum of all of
this. Right? So, I'll do that.
Right? And I'll
take the average. So, that's that's
essentially what whatever that average
will converge to is my
expected value for this. So, this is
essentially what I mean. When I say GT
such that ST equal to S
that means I'll start with S.
Okay? And compute this
rewards. Okay?
Right? So, is it clear why we need to
condition on the pi as well?
Right? The future is going to depend on
pi.
Yeah. Yeah. They I'm talking about
expectation here. I'm just explaining to
you what the expectation is.
So, every time I generate a trajectory
through pi,
right? Two things could happen.
A, I could pick different actions
because pi is stochastic.
B,
the world could change in a different
way because the world is stochastic. So,
in the same S, I could take the same A,
I might end up in a different S prime.
Every [snorts] time. Right? So, there
are multiple ways in which this
stochasticity can operate. So, one, pi
itself is stochastic, therefore, in the
same S, I need not take the same action
again. Say, first time I can take A1,
next time I can take A2, and so on and
so forth. Right? That will completely
change the trajectory that will come
later. Or,
I'll take the same A,
right? I might end up in a different S
prime
because of the transition probability.
So, every time I do this trajectory,
I'll get some different traject I mean,
every time I generate a trajectory, I'll
get a different sequence.
Right? And the expectation is over all
such sequences.
You know, [snorts] what is the total
reward I'll get? So, that's essentially
what the value function is.
Okay?
Is it clear?
Great. Let's Let's
confuse people some more.
[snorts]
So, we had Q earlier, right? So, what
was Q of A?
Q star of A was the true thing. Q of A
is the
expectation your expected estimate for
taking action A. Right?
But then here we have to worry about
taking action A in a specific state.
Because every state it is going to be
different.
Correct? Every state it will be
different. So what will this be?
Still have to do this. Still have to do
this.
So what is the big difference between
the V and Q?
Hm?
Action A is fixed in state. Sorry?
Action A is fixed in Yeah, action A is
fixed in. So earlier when you are
generating trajectories for V pi, I said
you start with S.
Right? Then you go to S prime.
Then you go to S double prime and so on
so forth. And then you could I said you
could pick any action here. So first
time you'll pick A, then A prime so next
time
you'll pick some A1.
So like this, right? So you could pick
different actions every time you
generated the trajectory. So now I'm
saying you can't do that.
Right? So every time you generate the
trajectory you have to pick A first.
Right? But subsequently you pick actions
according to
pi.
Right? So first action is something that
is fixed now. The first action will be A
all the time.
So what does this tell you? It tells you
how good is it to perform action A in a
given state.
So earlier you did not have that
information.
But now you have the information about
how good is it to perform
action A in a
given state.
Okay?
Is it clear?
Going back and thinking about the
problem itself, right? So, there is a
problem that we are trying to solve,
right? So, how do you define the
problem? How do you characterize the
problem?
Right? So, I'm in a state S.
I take an action.
Okay, I go to a next state.
And I also get a reward.
Right? So, for me to characterize the
problem,
I need to tell you how this transitions
happen.
And how the reward generation happens.
Right? So, I need to really look at this
following question. What is the
probability of
given
Sorry, not 8 minutes.
R T + 1 given
Is it sufficient?
I mean,
think about it, right? Riding a bicycle.
So, you probably need to know what
what is the velocity momentum that you
had before? I mean, it's not it's not
enough to know
how where you are on the road and how
you are tilting. You might want to know
something more about the history of how
you got there.
Right?
Right? So, you really need that
quantity.
Okay? So, you need to know what is the
probability of ST + 1 RT + 1
given everything that went before that.
[clears throat]
Correct? Now, this becomes a little
complex to model because the number of
parameters you will need for modeling
something like this becomes pretty
a pretty huge, right? So, what we
typically end up doing is make a very
strong assumption that this guy is equal
to
See, what we truly need is the first
quantity.
Right? Because it becomes
very hard to estimate, very hard to
define.
You make the assumption that that
quantity is really equal to this.
Right? So, what is this assumption
called typically?
Markov assumption. It's essentially a
first-order Markov assumption.
Uh
where the history doesn't matter.
Right? Only the current state and
current action matters. That will
determine what the next state and next
action will be. Right?
Uh so, we make a further assumption
which is
[clears throat]
What is the assumption I made?
Stationary.
Right? So, we'll typically operate in
Markov environments.
Right? And we'll typically assume they
are stationary.
Okay? So, for me to characterize the
problem, now what should I give you?
What I need is
What What is the question?
Yeah, to to specify the problem, what
are the things I should give you? Okay?
I should give you the
states over which the problem is
defined.
Right? I need to do that, right? I need
to define the state space over which the
problem is defined, and then
the set of actions
that I can take.
And
right? The P
function.
Right? So, I need all of this to define
the
problem completely. Anything else I
need?
Depends on what is the return I'm using.
I might also need a
gamma.
Right? If my If my return If I'm using a
discounted return, depending on what the
value of gamma is, the problem changes,
right? That's what we discussed.
So, if I'm going to use discounted
return, I should also specify gamma as
part of the
problem. Okay? So, is it clear? So, I
need all of this to define my
problem. Right? In some cases, we use a
slightly
simplified
definition.
Where, instead of having the single
joint distribution
is over S prime and R,
right? We also give it as two separate
quantities.
So, I'll suggest yes. I mean, I have to
specify S A.
Then, I'll specify
that.
So, what is that called? Sometimes
called the
the transition function or transition
probabilities. Okay? And then,
I'll specify the
the expected value of
the return
given that
[snorts]
at T, I was in S,
I did action A, and I went to S prime.
Right? So, essentially, I'm writing this
out splitting this up, right?
So, So, instead of giving my joint
distribution, I'm saying, "Okay, no, no.
I'll specify the S prime separately.
And for the R, I'll condition it on S
prime, also."
Right? So, I can you can think of some
sense I'm using the chain rule and uh
splitting the joint probability as P of
S prime into P of R given S A S prime.
But, what is the difference here?
Instead of specifying P of R given S A S
prime
I'm giving you only the
first moment yeah first moment or zeroth
moment.
I'm giving the first moment of the
distribution, right?
So
why is this enough?
Why is this enough?
It gives to maximize only the expected
value. Because I'm going to be
optimizing only the expected value of
GT, right? And GT is composed of these
guys,
right? So essentially I'll be taking the
individual expectations of each one of
these,
right? And that's enough for me. I don't
really need to know the
distribution that generated these
rewards because individually I'll be
taking the expectations of each one of
these rewards and therefore knowing the
expectation alone is enough. So
sometimes you specify the
problem like this.
Right? And this is typically how you
would
how would specify a what is called a
Markov decision process.
So it's it's a system
is a decision system that you have to
for every state you have to actually
keep giving a decision, right? And it
follows Markovian dynamics,
right? Both the transition and the
rewards follow
have I mean satisfy the Markov property,
right?
So such a
system is called a Markov decision
process.
Right? So you have states, you have set
of decisions,
right? And the evolution of the states
follows the
follows the Markov process. Okay, so
they are called Markov decision
processes.
Okay? And what we will assume is that
the reinforcement learning problems that
we are trying to solve can be modeled as
MDPs.
Okay?
We'll assume that the reinforcement
learning problems you're trying to solve
can be modeled as MDPs. So, in some
sense, a value function
really, you know, is useful only if you
have the Markov property.
Right?
Cuz I'm assigning a value to a state
regardless of how I got to the state.
Right? So, if my the Markov property is
not satisfied, how I got to the state
will influence what happens in the
future.
Right? Since I'm saying that, "Oh, I
don't care about what happened in the
past. I'm just saying I'm starting in
state S." Okay? And I'm going to be
following policy pi hereafter, what is
the expected return? Therefore, I'm
saying history is irrelevant.
Right? When I'm when I'm defining a
value function.
Another way of thinking about it is here
the value function is marginalizing over
history.
So, it's essentially taking the
expectation regardless of what the
history was.
That's one way of looking at it. I mean,
in some cases, that is how you make
sense out of the value functions.
Because
uh as we go along later, we'll see that
we actually apply RL blindly to problems
that are non-Markov.
Right? And we will be using we the V
function and the Q function
in such cases. So, the only way to make
sense out of what is happening in such
cases is to say that, "Hey, we're
essentially
marginalizing the history." So, we're
just doing the taking the expectation
over all possible histories as well.
It may or may not be a sensible
quantity, but uh if it works, hey,
you just use it. Right?
But
normally, the value function makes sense
only if you have the Markov property.
Forget about the future, right? And the
because you're ignoring the past, it
makes sense only if you have the Markov
property.
Right?
Does it make sense?
Right? So, that is why I was saying that
I should have probably defined value
functions after telling you what
Markov decision processes, but it's
okay. You can
still
understand it in the general sense as
well.
Great. So, the next thing we have to
talk about is optimal value functions.
And then I'll start that in the next
class.
[music]